So on my way here,
في طريقي إلى هنا،
the passenger next to me and I had a very interesting conversation
أجريت محادثة شيقة مع الراكب الذي بجانبي
during my flight.
خلال رحلتي
He told me, "It seems like the United States has run out of jobs,
قال لي :"يبدو أن الولايات المتحدة تُعاني من البطالة
because they're just making some up:
لأنهم يختلقون بعض الوظائف فقط:
cat psychologist, dog whisperer, tornado chaser."
كعالم نفس القطط و مدرب للكلاب و متعقب الأعاصير"
A couple of seconds later, he asked me,
بعد بضعة ثوان سألني:
"So what do you do?"
إذن ما عملك ؟
And I was like, "Peacebuilder?"
وقلت له :"داعية للسلام "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Every day, I work to amplify the voices of women
كل يوم أعمل لدعم صوت النساء،
and to highlight their experiences
ولتسليط الضوء على تجاربهن
and their participation in peace processes and conflict resolution,
ومشاركاتهن في عمليات السلام و حل النزاعات.
and because of my work,
وبسب عملي
I recognize that the only way to ensure the full participation of women globally
أدركت أن الطريقة الوحيدة لضمان المشاركة الكلية للنساء عالميًا
is by reclaiming religion.
هي عن طريق استعادة الدين.
Now, this matter is vitally important to me.
والآن، هذا الموضوع في غاية الأهمية لدي
As a young Muslim woman, I am very proud of my faith.
كامرأة مسلمة شابة ، أنا فخورة جدًا بديني.
It gives me the strength and conviction to do my work every day.
فهو يعطيني القوة والقناعة لإتمام عملي كل يوم.
It's the reason I can be here in front of you.
وهو السبب في وقوفي أمامكم.
But I can't overlook the damage that has been done in the name of religion,
لكن لا يمكنني ان أتغاضى عن الضرر الذي حصل باسم الدين،
not just my own, but all of the world's major faiths.
ليس ديني فقط، ولكن كل الديانات في العالم.
The misrepresentation and misuse and manipulation of religious scripture
التحريف وسوء الاستخدام والتلاعب بالنصوص المقدسة
has influenced our social and cultural norms,
كل هذا أثر على معاييرنا الاجتماعية والثقافية،
our laws, our daily lives,
و قوانينا وحياتنا اليومية،
to a point where we sometimes don't recognize it.
إلى حد لا ندركه في بعض الأحيان.
My parents moved from Libya, North Africa, to Canada
انتقل والديّ من ليبيا في شمال افريقيا لكندا
in the early 1980s,
في أوائل سنة 1980.
and I am the middle child of 11 children.
وأنا الطفلة الوسطى من بين 11 طفلًا.
Yes, 11.
نعم،11.
But growing up, I saw my parents,
و خلال نشأتي رأيت والديّا
both religiously devout and spiritual people,
متدينين و روحانين؛
pray and praise God for their blessings,
يصلون لله و يحمدونه على نعمه.
namely me of course, but among others. (Laughter)
أعني رأيت هذا بطبيعة الحال ، ولكن مع آخرين (ضحك)
They were kind and funny and patient,
كانا لطيفين ومضحكين وصبورين،
limitlessly patient, the kind of patience that having 11 kids forces you to have.
صبورين بلا حدود، وجود11 طفلا يفرض عليك هذا الصبر.
And they were fair.
و كانا عادلين.
I was never subjected to religion through a cultural lens.
لم أخضع قط للدين من خلال منظار ثقافي.
I was treated the same,
تمت معاملتي بالمثل،
the same was expected of me.
وكان متوقع مني نفس الشيء.
I was never taught that God judged differently based on gender.
لم أفكر مطلقًا أن الله يحاسب على أساس النوع.
And my parents' understanding of God as a merciful and beneficial friend
و كانت معرفة والديّ عن الله بأنه صديق رحيم و نافع
and provider shaped the way I looked at the world.
ومعطاء، قد شكلت طريقي في النظر للعالم.
Now, of course, my upbringing had additional benefits.
و بالطبع لنشأتي منفعة إضافية.
Being one of 11 children is Diplomacy 101. (Laughter)
أن تكون من بين 11 طفلا هو مدخل إلى الدبلوماسية 101.(ضحك)
To this day, I am asked where I went to school,
ليومنا هذا يتم سؤالي :في أي مدرسة درستِ؟
like, "Did you go to Kennedy School of Government?"
مثل: "هل درستِ في كلية كينيدي بهارفرد؟"
and I look at them and I'm like, "No,
وأنظر إليهم وأجيبهم قائلة " لا "،
I went to the Murabit School of International Affairs."
درست في مدرسة المرابط للشؤون الدولية"
It's extremely exclusive. You would have to talk to my mom to get in.
هي حصرية للغاية، عليك التكلم مع أمي للالتحاق بها.
Lucky for you, she's here.
من حسن حظكم أنها هنا.
But being one of 11 children and having 10 siblings
أن تكون من بين 11 طفلًا ولديك 10 أشقاء
teaches you a lot about power structures and alliances.
يعلمك الكثير عن هياكل القوة والتحالفات.
It teaches you focus; you have to talk fast or say less,
و التركيز، عليك التكلم بسرعة أو الاختصار،
because you will always get cut off.
لأنه سوف تتم مقاطعتك دائما.
It teaches you the importance of messaging.
يعلمك أهمية المراسلة.
You have to ask questions in the right way to get the answers you know you want,
عليك طرح أسئلة بطريقة صحيحة لتحصل على الإجابات المقنعة،
and you have to say no in the right way to keep the peace.
و عليك أن تقول لا بالشكل الصحيح ليبقى السلام.
But the most important lesson I learned growing up
ولكن أهم درس تعلمته خلال نشأتي
was the importance of being at the table.
هو أهمية أن تكون مشاركا .
When my mom's favorite lamp broke, I had to be there when she was trying
عندما يكسر مصباح أمي المفضل، علي أن أكون هناك عندما تحاول
to find out how and by who, because I had to defend myself,
اكتشاف كيف و من فعل هذا لأدافع عن نفسي،
because if you're not, then the finger is pointed at you,
لأنك إذا لم تقم بذلك، فستُوجّه إليك أصابع الاتهام،
and before you know it, you will be grounded.
وقبل معرفتك بذلك، ستُعاقب.
I am not speaking from experience, of course.
بطبيعة الحال أنا لا أتكلم عن خبرة.
When I was 15 in 2005, I completed high school and I moved
عندما كنت 15 سنة في 2005 أنهيت الثانوية وانتقلت
from Canada -- Saskatoon --
من كندا -- ساسكاتون --
to Zawiya, my parents' hometown in Libya,
للزاوية ، ،مسقط رأس أبي وأمي في ليبيا،
a very traditional city.
مدينة تقليدية جدا.
Mind you, I had only ever been to Libya before on vacation,
تذكروا، لم أذهب قطّ إلى ليبيا في عطلة،
and as a seven-year-old girl, it was magic.
وكطفلة في السابعة من عمرها، كان ذلك كالسحر.
It was ice cream and trips to the beach and really excited relatives.
كانت مثلجات ورحلات للشاطئ وأقارب ممتعين.
Turns out it's not the same as a 15-year-old young lady.
بالنظر إلى ذلك، اتضح انه ليس نفس الشعور لفتاة في الخامسة عشرة.
I very quickly became introduced to the cultural aspect of religion.
وسرعان ما تم تقديمي للجانب الثقافي الديني
The words "haram" -- meaning religiously prohibited --
كلمة "حرام"-- تعني ممنوعٌ دينيًا
and "aib" -- meaning culturally inappropriate --
و"عيب" غير لائق ثقافيًا--
were exchanged carelessly,
يتم استعمال المفردتين دون إيلاء أهمية للفرق بينهم،
as if they meant the same thing and had the same consequences.
كما لو أن لهن نفس المعنى ونفس النتائج.
And I found myself in conversation after conversation with classmates
ووجدت نفسي في نقاشات متتابعة مع زملائي في الدراسة
and colleagues, professors, friends, even relatives,
و الزملاء والأساتذة والأصدقاء، وحتى الأقارب،
beginning to question my own role and my own aspirations.
قد بدأوا التساءل حول دوري وطموحاتي.
And even with the foundation my parents had provided for me,
وبالرغم من الأسس التي زودني بها والديّ
I found myself questioning the role of women in my faith.
فإني وجدت نفسي أتساءل عن دور المرأة في ديني
So at the Murabit School of International Affairs,
لذلك في مدرسة المرابط للشؤون الدوليّة،
we go very heavy on the debate,
تعمقنا كثيرا في النقاش،
and rule number one is do your research, so that's what I did,
والقاعدة رقم 1 كانت أن أبحث، و هذا ما فعلته،
and it surprised me how easy it was
وتفاجأت كم كان يسيرًا
to find women in my faith who were leaders,
أن أعثر على نساء قائدات في ديني،
who were innovative, who were strong --
ممن كن مبتكرات وقويات --
politically, economically, even militarily.
سياسيًا و اقتصاديًا و عسكريًا حتى.
Khadija financed the Islamic movement
خديجة رضي الله عنها هي من موّلت الحركة الإسلامية
in its infancy.
في مرحلتها الأولى.
We wouldn't be here if it weren't for her.
لم نكن لنكون هنا هذا اليوم لو لم يكن ذلك لأجلها.
So why weren't we learning about her?
إذن لماذا لم نكن نتعلم عنها؟
Why weren't we learning about these women?
لماذا لا نتعلم عن هؤلاء النساء ؟
Why were women being relegated to positions which predated
لماذا يتم إبعاد المرأة للمواقع التي سبقت
the teachings of our faith?
تعاليم ديننا ؟
And why, if we are equal in the eyes of God,
ولماذا ؟ -إن كنا متساوين عند الله-
are we not equal in the eyes of men?
لسنا متساوين في أعين الرجال ؟
To me, it all came back to the lessons I had learned as a child.
بالنسبة لي، يعود كل ذلك للدروس التي تعلمتها في صغري.
The decision maker, the person who gets to control the message,
صانع القرار، الشخص الذي يسيطر على الرسالة
is sitting at the table,
جالس على الطاولة،
and unfortunately, in every single world faith,
ولسوء الحظ في كل ديانة عالمية
they are not women.
ليس هناك نساء.
Religious institutions are dominated by men
المؤسسات الدينية مسيطر عليها من قبل الرجال
and driven by male leadership,
يقودها الرجال
and they create policies in their likeness,
و قد أنشأوا سياسات حسب رغباتهم،
and until we can change the system entirely,
وإلى أن نستطيع تغيير النظام بأكمله
then we can't realistically expect to have full economic
فنحن في الحقيقة لا نتوقّع مشاركة
and political participation of women.
كليّة للمرأة اقتصاديًا وسياسيًا.
Our foundation is broken.
أساسنا معطل.
My mom actually says, you can't build a straight house on a crooked foundation.
قالت أمي لا تستطيع بناء منزل سليم على أساس أعوج.
In 2011, the Libyan revolution broke out, and my family was on the front lines.
في 2011، اندلعت الثورة الليبية، وكانت عائلتي على خطوط المواجهة.
And there's this amazing thing that happens in war,
وهناك الشيء المدهش الذي يحدث في الحرب،
a cultural shift almost, very temporary.
و هو تقريبا تحوّل ثقافي، مُؤقّت جدا.
And it was the first time that I felt it was not only acceptable
وكانت المرة الأولى التي شعرت فيها ليس فقط بقبولي
for me to be involved, but it was encouraged.
للمشاركة ولكن شعرت بتشجيعي.
It was demanded.
لقد كان مطلوبًا.
Myself and other women had a seat at the table.
أنا ونساء أخريات كان لنا مقاعد على الطاولة
We weren't holding hands or a medium.
لم نكن في الخلف أو مشجعات فقط.
We were part of decision making.
كنا جزءا من صانعي القرار.
We were information sharing. We were crucial.
كنا نتبادل المعلومات، كنا في غاية الأهمية.
And I wanted and needed for that change to be permanent.
وأردت واحتجت لذلك التغيير أن يكون دائما.
Turns out, that's not that easy.
اتضح لي، أن الأمر ليس بتلك السهولة.
It only took a few weeks before the women that I had previously worked with
استمر فقط بضعة أسابيع قبل أن تعود النساء
were returning back to their previous roles,
اللواتي عملت معهنّ إلي أدوارهنّ السابقة.
and most of them were driven by words of encouragement
و معظمهن تم طردهن بتشجيع
from religious and political leaders,
من قادة دينيين وسياسيين.
most of whom cited religious scripture as their defense.
و معظمهم استشهد بآيات قرآنية كدفاع عن أنفسهم
It's how they gained popular support for their opinions.
وهي طريقة اكتسابهم للدعم الشعبي لآرائهم.
So initially, I focused on the economic and political empowerment of women.
لذا ركزت في البداية على تعزيز مكانة المرأة اقتصاديا وسياسيا.
I thought that would lead to cultural and social change.
اعتقدت أن ذلك سيُحدث تغييرا ثقافيا واجتماعيا.
It turns out, it does a little, but not a lot.
اتضح أنه كان تغييرا طفيفا جدا وليس بصفة كُليّة.
I decided to use their defense as my offense,
قررت استخدام دفاعاتهم على أنها طريقة هجومي،
and I began to cite and highlight Islamic scripture as well.
وبدأت بالاستشهاد بأيات قرآنية كذلك.
In 2012 and 2013, my organization led the single largest
في 2012 و2013، قادت منظمتي واحدة من أكبر
and most widespread campaign in Libya.
وأكثر الحملات انتشارا في ليبيا.
We entered homes and schools and universities, even mosques.
دخلنا البيوت والمدارس والجامعات وحتى المساجد .
We spoke to 50,000 people directly,
تحدثنا مع 50,000 شخص مباشرة
and hundreds of thousands more through billboards and television commercials,
ومئات الآلاف من خلال اللوحات والإعلانات التلفزيونية
radio commercials and posters.
و الإذاعية والملصقات.
And you're probably wondering how a women's rights organization
وعلى الأرجح أنكم تتساءلون كيف يمكن لمنظمة حقوق المرأة
was able to do this in communities which had previously opposed
القيام بذلك في مجتعات عارضت في السابق
our sheer existence.
مجرد وجودنا.
I used scripture.
استخدمت نصوصا مقدسة.
I used verses from the Quran and sayings of the Prophet,
آيات قرآنية وأحاديث نبوية.
Hadiths, his sayings which are, for example,
الأحاديث ،أقواله على سبيل المثال،
"The best of you is the best to their family."
"خيركم خيركم لأهله "
"Do not let your brother oppress another."
" انصر أخاك ظالمًا أو مظلوما "
For the first time, Friday sermons led by local community imams
و لأول مرة دعا خطباء الجُمع في المجتمع المحلي
promoted the rights of women.
لتعزيز حقوق المرأة.
They discussed taboo issues, like domestic violence.
ناقشوا القضايا المحرمة، مثل العنف المنزلي
Policies were changed.
تغيرت السياسات .
In certain communities, we actually had to go as far
في مجتمعات معينة كان علينا أن نذهب لأقصى حد
as saying the International Human Rights Declaration,
مثل الإعلان الدولي العالمي لحقوق الانسان،
which you opposed because it wasn't written by religious scholars,
يمكن معارضته لأنه لم يكتب بواسطة علماء الدين.
well, those same principles are in our book.
حسنا،هذه نفس المبادئ في كتابنا.
So really, the United Nations just copied us.
لذلك قامت الأمم المتحدة باستنساخنا فقط.
By changing the message, we were able to provide
وعن طريق تغيير الرسالة كنا قادرين على توليد
an alternative narrative which promoted the rights of women in Libya.
رواية بديلة دعمت حقوق النساء في ليبيا.
It's something that has now been replicated internationally,
إنه شيء تم استنساخه الآن دوليا،
and while I am not saying it's easy -- believe me, it's not.
و أؤكد بأنه ليس سهلًا -- صدقوني إنه ليس كذلك.
Liberals will say you're using religion and call you a bad conservative.
سيقول الليبراليون بأنك تستخدم الدين وسيصمونك بالمحافظ الرجعي
Conservatives will call you a lot of colorful things.
بينما سيصفك المحافظون بأشياء كثيرة ومختلفة.
I've heard everything from, "Your parents must be extremely ashamed of you" --
لقد سمعت كل شيء: مثل "يجب على والديك أن يشعرا بالعار"--
false; they're my biggest fans --
مخطؤون فهما من أكبر المعجبين --
to "You will not make it to your next birthday" --
" لن تصمدي لعيد ميلادك الثاني" --
again wrong, because I did.
مرة أخرى مخطؤون. لأنني صمدت.
And I remain
وبقيت
a very strong believer that women's rights and religion are not mutually exclusive.
مؤمنة قوية بأن حقوق المرأة والدين لا يتعارضان.
But we have to be at the table.
ولكن علينا أن نكون على الطاولة.
We have to stop giving up our position, because by remaining silent,
علينا أن نتوقّف عن التخلي عن مناصبنا لأننا عندما نصمت،
we allow for the continued persecution and abuse of women worldwide.
فإننا نسمح باستمرار الاضطهاد و الاعتداء على النساء في العالم.
By saying that we're going to fight for women's rights
و بالقول بأننا سنقاتل لأجل حقوق المرأة
and fight extremism with bombs and warfare,
ونحارب المتطرفين بالقنابل والحرب،
we completely cripple local societies which need to address these issues
فإننا نشلّ المجتمعات المحلية التي تحتاج لمعالجة هذه القضايا
so that they're sustainable.
لتدوم.
It is not easy, challenging distorted religious messaging.
ليس سهلا تحدّي الديانات المحرّفة.
You will have your fair share of insults and ridicule and threats.
سيكون لك حصة كافية من السخرية والإهانة والتهديد.
But we have to do it.
ولكن علينا القيام بذلك.
We have no other option than to reclaim the message of human rights,
ليس لدينا حلّ آخر سوى استعادة رسالة حقوق الانسان
the principles of our faith,
و مبادئ ديننا.
not for us, not for the women in your families,
ليس لنا، ليس للنساء في عائلتك،
not for the women in this room,
ليس لأجل النساء اللاتي في هذه القاعة،
not even for the women out there,
و لا لأجل النساء اللاتي خارجها،
but for societies that would be transformed
ولكن للمجتمعات التي سوف تتغير
with the participation of women.
بمشاركة النساء.
And the only way we can do that,
والطريقة الوحيدة لفعل ذلك
our only option,
و خيارنا الوحيد
is to be, and remain, at the table.
أن نكون ونبقى مشاركين.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)